Finding Aid for Thomas M. Donahue papers, 1939-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Thomas M. Donahue papers 1939-2002, 1980-1998
Donahue, Thomas M.
2.75 linear feet
07126 Aa 2
Thomas M. Donahue (1921-2004), space and planetary scientist and professor of physics, was one of the nation's pioneers in space exploration. He shaped space exploration through his scientific research and advocacy. The collection includes correspondence, proposals, presentations, talks, writings, and photographs reflecting his career and covers the years 1939-2002, but primarily documents the period 1980-1998.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers (donor no. 9607 ) were received from Esther Donahue on May 24, 2005
No further additions are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Thomas M. Donahue was born in Healdton, Oklahoma of Irish-American parents on May 23, 1921, and was raised in Kansas City, Missouri. He stayed in Missouri to complete his studies at Rockhurst College, and by 1942 he had earned degrees in both classics and physics. He left soon after to start graduate work in the physics department at Johns Hopkins University in Baltimore. His work was waylaid in 1944-1945 by service in the Signal Corps of the United States Army. Returning to Johns Hopkins he received his PhD in atomic physics in the fall of 1947, and from 1948 to 1951 he was assistant professor of physics.
Following his appointment as assistant professor at Johns Hopkins, Donahue joined the University of Pittsburgh as an assistant professor in 1951 and by 1959 he was promoted to the rank of full professor of physics, serving until 1974. While at the University of Pittsburgh he organized an atomic physics and atmospheric science program that led to the experimental and theoretical study of the upper atmosphere of the Earth and spacecraft explorations of Mars, Venus, and the outer planets. By 1974, Donahue concurrently held two director positions, one at the Space Research Coordination Center, 1970-1974 and the other at the Laboratory for Atmospheric and Space Science from 1966 to 1974.
In 1974 Donahue joined the University of Michigan faculty as chairman of the Department pf Atmospheric and Oceanic Science, a position he held until 1980. Throughout his research and teaching career at the University of Michigan he was regarded as the foremost expert on the atmosphere and ionosphere of Venus, as well as how atmospheric chemistry influenced the evolution and behavior of planets. As such, Donahue pursued his growing interest in the problem of anthropogenic destruction of the stratospheric ozone by founding and directing the Project for the Integrated Study of Global Change from 1990-1992.
Donahue displayed a strong commitment to atmospheric science and space research through his professional activities and associations. During his early work with the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) he was Chairman of the steering group responsible for two Venus missions. He was also an experimenter on several missions including Apollo-17, Voyager, Galileo and the Cassini mission to Saturn and the outer planets. He was elected to the National Academy of Sciences in 1983 and was the chairman of the Space Science Board of the National Research Council (NRC) from 1982 to1988. He has also served on numerous governmental and scientific advisory boards and committees, such as the Committee on Atmosphere Sciences, Geophysics Research Board, and several university consortia working groups.
Donahue received many honors over the years. He won eight NASA Achievement Awards, several NASA Public Service Awards, and the Wellock Distinguished Research Accomplishment Award from the University of Michigan in 1981. In the same year he also received the distinguished Arctowski Medal from the NAS and the John Adams Fleming Medal from the American Geophysical Union. In 1988, he was given the Space Science Award from the American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics. Also notable is the Henry Russel Award of 1986, one of the highest honors bestowed upon a University of Michigan faculty member.
Donahue authored over 200 publications and was editor of Space Research X in 1970 and Venus in 1983. He was also associate editor of Reviews of Geophysics and Space Sciences-Planetary and Space Science.
Donahue was a lover of his Irish ancestry. He studied both oral and written sources and was known for his efforts to support the establishment of the International O'Donoghue Society. He was survived by his wife Esther, and three sons: Brian, Kevin, and Neil.
_ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _
Sources:
Biographical sketch and resume, 12/18/1996, Biographical Folder- Box 1.
"Thomas Donahue, 83, Expert On Space Exploration of the Planets," New York Times [Obituary] October 19, 2004.
Engineering Faculty Pages: http://data.engin.umich.edu/faculty_staff/faculty/Donahue.html
Thomas M. Donahue, 1921-2004, Daily Planet, Fall 2004.
[Obituary- Thomas Donahue]. The University Record Online, URL as of 6/27/2006: http://www.umich.edu/-urecord/0405/Oct25 04/obits.shtml
Planetary Scientist Donahue Dies at 83 The Ann Arbor News, B5, October 20, 2004.
In Memoriam News of Michigan Physics, vol. 18 no. 1, Fall/Winter 2004, page 9.
The Thomas Donahue papers include correspondence, proposals, presentations, talks, writings, and photographs reflecting his career. The papers, 2.75 linear feet, date from 1939 to 2002, but primarily document the period 1980-1998. The papers are organized into five series: Biographical; Presentations, Talks, and Writings; Professional Activities; University of Michigan; and Correspondence.
Subjects:
Donahue, Thomas M.; Space sciences.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Atmospheric, Oceanic and Space Sciences.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Venus (Planet)--Atmosphere.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical
  The Biographical series (0.2 linear feet) includes versions of Donahue's curriculum vitae, lists of publications, and brief biographical statements along with scattered clippings. Also included are photographs of Donahue, both portraits, candid, and in groups. The photographs are undated but cover roughly 1950 to 2000.
  Presentations, Talks, and Writings, 1939-1988 (1.0 linear feet) is a chronologically arranged sequence containing Donahue's presentations, talks, and writings. Included in this series are transcripts of testimonies given before government committees, both published and unpublished research writings, biographical records, lectures, and editorials. Also contained in this series are photos of Donahue and a VHS videotape of his lecture on "The Galileo Mission to Jupiter."
  - Biographical 1970-1997 (Box 1)
  - Photos undated (Box 1)
- Presentations, Talks, and Writings 1939-1998, undated
  - Chronological
    - Civilization, Culture, and Today and God December 18, 1939 (Box 1)
    - Radiative Transfer in Planetary Atmospheres and Astronomy 1966 (Box 1)
    - FAA Hearing on Concorde April 14, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Effect of Odd Hydrogen on Ozone Depletion by Chlorine Reactions February 1976 (Box 1)
    - Ultraviolet Stellar Occultation Measurement of the H2 and 02 Densities Near 100 km in the Earth's Atmosphere 1976 (Box 1)
    - A Program of Stratospheric Research July 1977 (Box 1)
    - Oxides of Nitrogen and the Clouds of Venus circa 1979 (Box 1)
    - Lessons from Venus (draft) March 8, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Comparative Planetology of Atmospheres (Presentation to the Solar System Exploration Committee April 20, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Impact of the ISPM Decision on International Cooperation and Relations with the Scientific Community July 28, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Copernicus Measurement of the Jovian Lyman-Alpha Emission in 1980 and its Aeronomical Significance, January 24, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Direction of the Development of a Civil Space Station November 15, 1983 (Box 1)
    - FY '85 Budget Request March 5, 1984 (Box 1)
    - [Bevilacqua Paper (1983)] April 5, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Letter to the Brown Alumni Monthly February 25, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Water Vapor in the Atmosphere of Venus April 8, 1985 (Box 1)
    - [Talk on Fred] September 30, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Discussion of Mankind's Effect on the Stratospheric Ozone September 30, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Mission to Planet Earth November 13, 1985 (Box 1)
    - [FY '86 Budget Request] circa 1986 (Box 1)
    - [FY '1987 NASA Budget Authorization] February 27, 1986 (Box 1)
    - [FY '87 Budget Request] April 10, 1986 (Box 1)
    - The Nation's Space Program After Challenger: The Roles of Manned and Unmanned Systems for Launching Scientific Space Missions May 21, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Assured Access to Space: Payload Priorities July 21, 1986 (Box 1)
    - [Hearing on] Assessment of Science Recommendations in Paine Commission Report and Implications for Space Science Program of Challenger Loss July 22, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Report to the National Commission on Space July 23, 1986 (Box 1)
    - How the Planets Got and Lost Their Atmospheres and Oceans April 10, 1987 (Box 1)
    - On the Matter of Resignation of the Chairman of the Space Science Board April 13, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Introduction to Space Science Issue April 13, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Solar Cycle of H+ and D+ Densities in the Venus Ionosphere: Implications for Escape circa 1992 (Box 1)
    - Hydrogen and Sculpture Compounds on Venus 1992 (Box 1)
    - High Resolution Studies of Upper Atmospheric Weather February 6, 1992 (Box 1)
    - EOS Report Contribution: Venus Symposium, August 17,1992 (Box 1)
    - The Aeronomical Pilgrim's Progress 1995 (Box 1)
    - Evolution of Water Reservoirs on Mars from D/H Ratios in the Atmosphere and Crust March 30, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Waynick Lecture: The Galileo Mission to Jupiter (VHS Videotape) April 12, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Scientific Interpretation of Galileo Probe Mass Spectrometer Measurements 1997 (Box 1)
    - Composition of the Joint Atmosphere as Determined by the Galileo Probe Mass Spectrometer circa 1998 (Box 1)
  - Undated
    - A Call for A National Policy of Preeminence in Space Science (Box 1)
    - Comets and Water on Venus: Venus Was Wet undated (Box 1)
    - Comparative Planetology of Venus and Earth undated (Box 1)
    - Experiment and Operations Sequence for ISO-SL 1 undated (Box 1)
    - An Interpretation of the Voyager Measurement of Jovian Electron Density Profiles undated (Box 1)
    - Interstellar Medium and Small Comet Contribution to Hydrogen Lyman-Emission undated (Box 1)
    - Methane Measurement by the Pioneer Venus Large Probe Neutral Mass Spectrometer undated (Box 1)
    - [National Aeronautics and Space Act of 1958] undated (Box 1)
    - Planets undated (Box 1)
    - Science and the Space Station undated (Box 1)
    - Space Science in the Twenty-First Century: A Study by the Space Science Board undated (Box 1)
    - Temperatures in a Postulated Steam Atmosphere, and Implications for History of Water on Venus undated (Box 1)
    - Venus Methane and Hydrogen undated (Box 1)
    - Water on Terrestrial Planets (Abstract) undated (Box 1)
    - Why Explore Venus? undated (Box 1)
- Professional Activities 1971-2004, undated
  Professional Activities, 1971-2004 (0.50 linear feet) is an alphabetically arranged sequence documenting Thomas Donahue's professional activity within scientific organizations, committees, and advisory boards, research related working groups, and national symposiums. Of particular note is Donahue's involvement with the National Academy of Sciences, where he served as chairman of the Space Science Board from 1982 to 1988. Also contained in this series is research-related correspondence of the Noble Gas Group, as well as a small amount of National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) material concerning the Voyager and Challenger missions.
  - American Geophysical Union (AGU)
    - Committee on Public Affairs 1990-1992 (Box 1)
    - Spring Session 1998 (Box 1)
  - Arecibo Advisory Board 1985-1989, undated (Box 1)
  - Consortium for the International Earth Science Information Network (CIESIN) 1990 (Box 1)
  - Committee to Visit the Department of Earth and Planetary Science (Harvard) 1994-1997 (Box 1)
  - National Academy of Sciences (NAS)
    - Correspondence 1984 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1986 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1987 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1988-2004 (Box 1)
    - Report Review Committee 1985 (Box 2)
    - Voyager Missions Symposium 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics (AIAA) 1983-1992 (Box 2)
    - Pioneer-Venus Orbiter Mission 1973-1978 (Box 2)
  - National Astronomy and Ionosphere Center Advisory Board (Arecibo Observatory 1971-1974 (Box 2)
  - National Balloon Facility (NSBF) 1985-1988 (Box 2)
  - Noble Gas Group (Research Related) 1996-1997
    - 1996, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1997 (Box 2)
    - Space Lab 1 1983 (Box 2)
  - Space Science Board (SSB)
    - Long-Range Study 1985 (Box 2)
    - Summer Study 1984 (Box 2)
    - USSR ESA Operations 1985 (Box 2)
  - Space Telescope Institute Visiting Committee 1987-1989 (Box 2)
  - Warren-Thompson Award Selection Committee 1985-1987 (Box 2)
- University of Michigan 1985-1993, undated
  University of Michigan, 1985-1993 (0.25 linear feet) is an alphabetically arranged sequence primarily documenting Donahue's involvement at the University of Michigan in the Department of Atmospheric and Oceanic Science, the Astrophysics Institute and the Global Change Project. Within this series are materials related to the Donahue Memorial Colloquium. Of particular note is a photo album of the Donahue Memorial Colloquium from 1992. The album includes a tribute letter from Pulitzer Prize winning writer Russell Baker who was a student of Donahue's at Johns Hopkins. Also included are photos from his Henry Russel Award Ceremony in 1986.
  - Atmospheric and Oceanic Science (AOS) Review Committee 1985-1986, undated (Box 2)
  - Astrophysics Institute 1988-1993 (Box 2)
  - Computation Notebook circa 1995 (Box 2)
  - Global Change Project (GCP)
    - Corporate Sponsors 1989-1991 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1989-1992, undated (Box 2)
    - Newspapers Articles 1990 (Box 2)
    - Proposal 1989-1992, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Senior Faculty Search Committee 1992 (Box 2)
    - Workshops 1988-1991 (Box 2)
  - Henry Russel Lecturer Award (includes photographs) 1986 (Box 2)
  - Donahue Memorial Colloquium
    - Invitations and Letters 1992 (Box 2)
    - James J. Duderstadt's Presentation November 1992 (Box 2)
    - Thomas Donahue's Speech 1992 (Box 2)
    - Photo Album (includes Russell Baker letter) (Box 2)
- Correspondence 1974-2002
  Correspondence, 1974-2002 (1.0 linear feet) is a chronologically arranged sequence of materials that documents Donahue's general communications concerning research, nominations, proposal reviews, publishing and editorials, professional activities, and a small amount of genealogy.
  - 1974-1982, 6 folders (Box 3)
  - 1983-1990, 8 folders (Box 3)
  - 1992, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - 1993, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1994-2002, 6 folders (Box 3)